Finding Aid for the Jonathan Friedlander Collection of Middle Eastern Americana LSC.1314
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Motion Picture Films, ca. 1975 - 2004; 6 boxes, 1 oversize box (3 linear feet)
  - DVDs, 1995 - 2004; 4 boxes (2 linear feet)
    - Exodus Metro Goldwyn Mayer, 2002., 1960; 1 videodisc (198 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 8, Folder 11)
      Back cover reads: "[...the] chronicle of the rebirth of a people and the establishment of a nation is the ultimate experience in human drama...Ari Ben Canaan, a commander in the Israeli underground, manages to lead 600 Jews from the detention camps in Cyprus onto a large freighter bound for Palestine. But British forces soon learn of his plan and insist that he turn back. Undaunted, Ari and his passengers refuse to give up, risking their lives for the greater cause of Israeli independence." Based on Leon Uris book.
    - House of sand and fog Dreamworks Pictures., 2003; 1 videodisc (126 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 8, Folder 12)
      Creator: Perelman, Vedel
      "Academy Award winner Ben Kingsley and Jennifer Connelly deliver stunning performances as two strangers whose conflicting pursuits of the American Dream lead to a fight for their hopes at any cost. What begins as a struggle over a rundown bungalow spirals into a clash that propels everyone involved toward a shocking resolution."
    - Intolerance Alpha Video, 2003., 1916; 1 videodisc (197 minutes): no sound, black & white, 4 3/4 inches (Box 8, Folder 13)
      Creator: Griffith, D.W.
    - Khartoum Metro Goldwyn Mayer, 2002., 1966; 1 videodisc (136 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 8, Folder 14)
      Creator: Dearden, Basil
      Back cover reads: "In 1883, British Prime Minister Gladstore dispatches General Charles Gordon to Khartoum, Sudan, where thousands of civilians are threatened by a Muslim fanatic, the Mahdi, and his army of followers. Gordon gains the Mahdi's respect but can't prevent the Mahdi's men from laying siege to the city. Now, as history hangs in the balance, Gordon faces the fight of his life defending the ancient city of Khartoum."
    - Lawrence of Arabia Columbia Pictures, 2000., 1962; 1 videodisc (217 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 8, Folder 15)
      Creator: Lean, David
    - Lawrence of Arabia: collector's edition Columbia Pictures, 2000., 1962; 1 videodisc (217 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 8, Folder 16)
      Insert includes text from original promotional materials.
    - Lion man Alpha Video, 2004., 1936; 1 videodisc (60 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Creator: McCarthy, John
      Back cover reads: "A wealthy explorer, Sir Ronald Chatham, accompanied by his young son, embarks on a dangerous scientific mission to search for valuable deposits of tungsten in the Arabian Desert. Crossing the desert sands on camelback, Sir Ronald's party is massacred by a tribe of evil Arabics and only the youngster survives–rescued by a mysterious white woman. Injured herself and near death, she leaves him in the care of a wizened desert mystic who lives peacefully alongside the lions. The old man takes the child in and raises him to manhood. Years later the handsome young man, now revered as "El Lion" by the Arabs, learns about the fate of his father and sets out to avenge his murder."
    - Mummy Universal Studio, 1999., 1932; 1 videodisc (74 minutes): sound, black & white, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Creator: Freund, Karl
      Back cover reads: "Boris Karloff's legendary performance has become a landmark in the annals of screen history. As the mummy, Im-Ho-Tep, he is accidently revived after 3700 years by a team of British archaeologists. It is revealed in a flashback that he was a high priest, embalmed alive for trying to revive the vestal virgin whom he loved, after she had been sacrificed. Alive again, he sets out to find his lost love."
    - Mummy Universal Studios., 1999; 1 videodisc (125 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Creator: Sommers, Stephen
      Back cover reads: "Deep in the Egyptian desert, a handful of people searching for a long-lost treasure have just unearthed a 3000 year old legacy of terror." Cover features three pyramids.
    - Mummy's shroud The Hammer Bay Collection, 1995., 1967; 1 videodisc (90 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Creator: Gilling, John (1912-1984)
      Back cover reads: "Beware the beat of the cloth-wrapped feet!"
    - Not without my daughter Metro Goldwyn Mayer, 2001., 1990; 1 videodisc (116 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Creator: Gilbert, Brian
      Back cover: "Betty has come to the Middle East with her daughter and native- born husband for a visit with his family. But soon the horrible truth about their 'vacation' surfaces. Betty's husband doesn't intend to bring his family back to America...ever. She may return, he says, but their daughter must stay. And he has centuries of local custom and the oppressive might of a police state behind him..."
    - Order Columbia Tristar Pictures., 2001; 1 videodisc (89 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Creator: Lettich, Sheldon
      Back cover reads: "Journey to a turbulent world under siege as reformed artifact smuggler Rudy travels to Jerusalem to rescue his musuem-curator father, who's been kidnapped by ruthless fanatics, and recover a sacred scroll believed to hold dangerous secrets of a underground sect. Framed for murder by a scheming police chief, Rudy enlists the aid a mysterious beauty to clear his name and wages a one-man battle to recapture the prized manuscript before the ultimate Holy War breaks out and all hell breaks loose."
    - Passion of the Christ 20th Century Fox., 2004; 1 videodisc (126 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Creator: Gibson, Mel
    - Road to Morocco Universal Studios, 2002., 1942; 1 videodisc (83 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Creator: Butler, David
      Back cover reads: "Survivors of a Mediterranean shipwreck, stowaways Jeff and Orville paddle to a North African shore and hitch a camel ride across the desert to Morocco. In order to buy food, Jeff sells Orville into slavery–but Orville's owner turns out to be the luscious Princess Shalmar, who quickly offers to become his wife." B&W 93 Mins
    - Rules of engagement Paramount Pictures., 2000; 1 videodisc (127 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Creator: Friedkin, William
      Back cover reads: "Colonel Terry Childers is a patriot and war hero. But when a peacekeeping mission he leads in Yemen goes terribly wrong, he finds himself facing a court martial. Accused of breaking the rules of engagement by killing unarmed civilians, Childers' only hope of vindication rests with comrade-in-arms Hays Hodges, a military lawyer of questionable abilities. Together, they face the battle of their lives."
    - Sheik and The son of the sheik Artcinema Corporation, 2002., 1926; 1 videodisc (155 minutes): no sound, black & white, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 10)
      Creator: Valentino, Rudolph
      Includes additional footage pertaining to the making of the film and newsreels from the film's release.
    - Siege 20th Century Fox., 1998; 1 videodisc (116 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 11)
      Creator: Zwick, Edward
      Back cover reads: "When a crowded city bus blows up in Brooklyn and a campaign of terror begins to make its bloody mark on the streets of New york, it's up to FBI special agent Anthony Hubbard and U.S. Army General William Devereaux to find out who's responsible...and put an end to the destruction. Together, they face explosive danger at every turn when they team up to wage an all-out war against a ruthless band of terrorists."
    - Sinbad: legend of the seven seas DreamWorks Pictures., 2003; 1 videodisc (86 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 12)
      Creator: Johnson, Tim
      Animated feature.
    - Sinbad: legend of the seven seas DreamWorks Pictures., 2003; 1 videodisc (86 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 12)
      Creator: Gilmore, Patrick
    - Stargate Artisan Entertainment, 2003., 1994; 1 videodisc (119 minutes): sound, black & white, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 13)
      Creator: Emmerich, Ronald
      Back cover reads: "When Professor Daniel Jackson innocently accepts the offer of a mysterious woman to decode an ancient Egyptian artifact known only as the Stargate, he unwittingly takes the first step on an epic adventure that will span galaxies and decide the fate of an entire planet."
    - Thief of Baghdad: an Arabian nights fantasy United Artists, 2004., 1924; 1 videodisc (154 minutes): no sound, color tinted, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 14)
      Creator: Walsh, Raoul
      Back cover reads: "...The Thief of Baghdad is a bold Arabian adventure starring Douglas Fairbanks as a carefree pickpocket who turns his appealing brand of mischievous thievery toward the attainment of happiness...and an exotic Princess. The only way he can win either is by retrieving the rarest treasures hidden within the mysterious Orient, a quest that grows more fantastic with every passing thrill, as the tenacious thief rises high above the city on a magic carpet, battles a fire-breathing dragon in caverns of flame and soars into the clouds on the back of a winged steed via innovative special effects."
    - Three kings Warner Brothers Pictures., 2000; 1 videodisc (115 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 15)
      Creator: Russel, David O.
      Back cover reads: "Three Kings begins when the Gulf War is over. Amid the partying and the confusion, four American soldiers, determined to take home more than sand fleas, go off into the Iraqi desert to find millions in stolen Kuwait bullion. They are plunged into the heart of a democratic uprising that spins the day and their lives out of control."
    - Three musketeers: volume 1 (chapters 1-6) Alpha Video, 2003., 1933; 1 videodisc (113 minutes): sound, black & white, 4 3/4 inches (Box 9, Folder 16)
      Creator: Schaefer, Armand & Clark, Colbert
      Role: directors
      Back cover reads "...Tom Wayne is a fugitive from justice, framed for a murder he did not commit. El Shaitan, the mysterious and diabolical leader of the Devil's Circle, a group who are plotting an Arab rebellion against the Foreign Legion, is to blame..."
    - Three musketeers: volume 2 (chapters 7-12) Alpha Video, 2003., 1933; 1 videodisc (113 minutes): sound, black & white, 4 3/4 inches (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Three stooges: all the world's a stooge Sony Pictures, 2000., ca. 1940; 1 videodisc (124 minutes): sound, black & white, 4 3/4 inches (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Creator: Lord, Del
      Collection of 7 short films from 1937-1946.
    - Wind and the lion Warner Brothers, 2004., 1975; 1 videodisc (119 minutes): sound, color, 4 3/4 inches (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Creator: Milus, John
      Back cover reads: "In 1904 Morocco, European powers desire a foothold in the Arab world–and [Arab desert chieftan] Raisuli is determined to stir up tribal fury against them. So he kidnaps an American widow and her children, igniting a chain of events that include President Theodore Roosevelt wielding the big stick of foreign policy and Raisuli matching wits and sharing mutual admiration with his lovely captive."
    - Yank in Libya Producers Releasing Corporation, 2004., 1942; 1 videodisc (66 minutes): sound, black & white, 4 3/4 inches (Box 11, Folder 2)
      Creator: Herman, Albert
      Back cover reads: "While traveling through the deserts of Libya, Mike Malone, a brash and cocky newspaper reporter, uncovers a Nazi plot to incite Arab tribes to arise and murder all Americans. When he tries to report the imminent danger to the British consul, no one wants to listen. He decides to investigate on his own."
  - Laserdisks, 1983 - 1992; 1 oversize box
    - Aladdin Burbank, CA: Walt Disney Home Video., 1994; 1 videodisc (90 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 1)
      Creator: Menken, Alan
      Cover features an illustration of Aladdin, Jasmine and Abu, Aladdin's pet monkey, carpet-flying over the city of Agrabah.
    - Aladdin Burbank, CA: Walt Disney Home Video., 1994; 1 videodisc (90 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Aladdin Burbank, CA: Walt Disney Home Video., 1994; 2 videodiscs (90 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 2)
      Cover features an illustration of Genie.
    - Aladdin Burbank, CA: Walt Disney Home Video., 1994; 2 videodiscs (90 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Ben-Hur New York, NY: MGM/UA Home Video, 1983., 1959; 2 videodiscs (211 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 3)
      Creator: Wyler, William, 1902-1981.
    - Casablanca Culver City, CA: MGM/UA Home Video., 1989; 1 videodisc (104 minutes): sound, black & white, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 4)
      Creator: Curtiz, Michael, 1888-1962
    - Casablanca Culver City, CA: MGM/UA Video., 1992; 1 videodisc (104 minutes): sound, black & white, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 5)
      Cover is an illustration of Humphrey Bogart and Ingrid Bergman.
    - Cleopatra Universal City, CA: MCA Home Video., 1988; 1 videodisc (100 minutes): sound, black & white, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 6)
      Creator: DeMille, Cecil B.; 1881-1959
      Cover is an illustration of Claudette Colbert as Cleopatra.
    - Gallipoli Hollywood, CA: Paramount., 1981; 1 videodisc (111 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 7)
      Creator: Weir, Peter, 1944-
    - Indiana Jones and the last crusade Paramount., 1989; 2 videodiscs (126 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 8)
      Creator: Spielberg, Steven, 1946-
      Cover features the promotional poster for the film.
    - Jesus Christ superstar Universal Studios., 1973; 1 videodisc (107 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 9)
      Creator: Jewison, Norman
      Cover features a photograph of the crucifixion scene from the film.
    - King of kings Warner Brothers., 1993; 2 videodisc (171 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 10)
      Creator: Hunter, Jeffrey, 1925-1969
    - Last temptation of Christ Universal City, CA: MCA Home Video., 1989; 2 videodiscs (143 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 11)
      Creator: Kazantzakis, Nikos, 1883-1957
    - Lawrence of Arabia Burbank, CA: Columbia Tristar Home Video., 1994; 2 videodiscs (217 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 12)
      Creator: Lean, David, 1908-
      Cover is a photo of Peter O'Toole as Lawrence of Arabia.
    - [Not without my daughter] Culver City, CA MGM/UA Home Video., 1991; 1 videodisc (107 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 13)
      Cover is a collage of photos from the film, featuring Sally Field in head covering. Jacket excerpt reads, "Betty has come to the Middle East with her daughter and native- born husband. It's just a vacation, her husband promises. But soon the horrible truth surfaces. Betty's husband doesn't intend to bring his family back to America ... ever."
    - [Not without my daughter] Culver City, CA MGM/UA Home Video., 1991; 1 videodisc (107 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 13)
      Creator: Riddle, Pat, 1938-
    - Raiders of the lost ark Hollywood, CA: Paramount Home Video., 1981; 2 videodiscs (115 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 14)
    - Sinbad and the eye of the tiger Sony Pictures., 1983; 1 videodisc, sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 15)
      Creator: Wanamaker, Sam, 1919-
      Cover includes pagan and orientalist images, including women in harem costume, a goat, a snake, an eagle, skeletons holding sabers, and a woman with talons for feet.
    - Sinbad collection Culver City, CA: Columbia TriStar Home Video., 1995; 4 videodiscs, sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 16)
      Creator: Harryhausen, Rey, 1920-
      Back cover reads: "All three of Ray Harryhausen's Sinbad films in one deluxe four-disc package."
    - Son of the sheik Kino Video, 1991., 1926; 1 videodisc (68 minutes): silent, black & white, with color tints, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 17)
      Creator: Fitzmaurice, George, 1885-1940
      Cover features a photograph of Rudolph Valentino and Vilma Banky.
    - Ten commandments Hollywood, CA: Paramount, undated., 1956; 2 videodiscs (220 minutes): sound, color, 12 inches (Box 51, Folder 18)
      Creator: DeMille, Cecil B.
  - VHS cassettes, ca. 1975 - 1998; 2 boxes (1 linear foot)
    This subseries includes cassette containers and sleeves only. Video cassettes are available through the Office of Instructional Development at the Instructional Media Lab in Powell Library at UCLA.
    - 13th warrior Buena Vista., 1999; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Creator: McTiernan, John
      Back cover reads: "An exiled ambassador far from his homeland, Ahmed comes across a fierce band of warriors who are being attacked by ferocious creatures legendary for devouring all living things in their path."
    - Abbott and Costello: meet the mummy Universal Pictures, 1993., 1955; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Creator: Lamont, Charles
      Back cover reads: "When Pete and Freddie, a couple of Americans stranded in Cairo, overhear an archaeologist chatter about discovering a legendary mummy, they decide to apply as chaperones for the corpse back to the United States."
    - Abbott and Costello: the foreign legion Universal Pictures, 1994., 1950; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 5)
      Back cover reads: "The chaos begins in Brooklyn. Jonesy and Max are wrestling promoters whose star fighter runs out on them. Following him to Algiers, they get more than they bargained for when they're tricked into joining the Foreign Legion."
    - Aladdin's Arabian adventures: creatures of invention Walt Disney Home Video., 1998; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Arabian nights Universal, 1993., 1942; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Creator: Rawlins, John
    - Ben-Hur Metro Goldwyn Mayer, 1996., 1959; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Creator: Wyler, William
    - Ben-Hur: a tale of the Christ Metro Goldwyn Mayer, 1988., 1927; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 9)
      Creator: Niblo, Fred
      Silent film classic retelling the famous novel by General Lew Wallace.
    - Cleopatra 20th Century Fox, 1992., 1963; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 10)
      Creator: Mankiewicz, Joseph L.
    - Golden voyage of Sinbad Columbia Tristar., 1973; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 11)
      Creator: Hessler, Gordon
    - Greatest story ever told Metro Goldwyn Mayer, 1998., 1965; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 12)
      Creator: Stevens, George
    - Indiana Jones and the last crusade Paramount, 1999., 1989; 1 videocassette container (Box 10, Folder 13)
      Creator: Spielberg, Steven
    - Ishtar Columbia Pictures, 1998., 1987; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Creator: May, Elaine
    - Jesus Christ superstar Universal, 1998., 1973; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Land of the pharaohs Warner Brothers, 1992., 1955; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Creator: Hawks, Howard
    - Last temptation of Christ Universal, 1996., 1988; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Creator: Scorsese, Martin
    - Marx brothers: a night in Casablanca United Artists, 1998., 1946; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Creator: Mayo, Archie
    - Mummy Universal Studios, 1991., 1932; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Back cover reads: "Karloff plays Im-Ho-Tep, the mummy, who is accidently revived after 3700 years by a British archaeology team."
    - Mummy Warner Brothers, 1989., 1959; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Creator: Fisher, Terence
      Back cover reads: "Torn from the tomb...to terrify"
    - Mummy lives Cannon Pictures., 1998; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 10)
      Creator: O'Hara, Gerry
      Back cover reads: "Tomb it may concern: Beware the Mummy's curse."
    - Omar Khayyam Paramount Pictures, 1992., 1956; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Creator: Dieterle, William
      Back cover reads: "Omar Khayyam dramatizes the renowned Persian's heroic life and times."
    - Road to Morocco Universal Studies, 1992., 1942; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 12)
      Back cover reads: "Survivors of a Mediterranean shipwreck, our Heroes find themselves in the company of Princess Shalmar, who has purchased Bob and plans to make him her husband."
    - Sheik Paramount, 1992., 1926; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 13)
      Creator: Melford, George
    - Sinbad and the eye of the tiger Columbia Tristar, 1991., 1977; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 14)
      Creator: Wanamaker, Sam
    - Solomon and Sheba United Artists, 1994., 1959; 1 videocassette container (Box 11, Folder 15)
      Creator: Vidor, King
- Arabian Nights Books, 1875 - 2005; 8 boxes, 1 oversize box (4 linear feet)
  This series consists of collected translations of and critical theory about the popular Arabian Nights stories, also known as One Thousand and One Nights, The Arabian Nights Entertainment, and Tales from the Arabian Nights.
  - 1001 Nights: illustrated fairy tales from one thousand and one nights Berlin: Die Gestalten Verlag GmbH., 2005; 157 pages, 24 centimeters (Box 29, Folder 1)
    Creator: Klanten, Robert
    Stories with illustrations by mostly European contemporary artists. Source of text unknown.
  - 1001 Nights: illustrated fairy tales from one thousand and one nights Berlin: Die Gestalten Verlag GmbH., 2005; 157 pages, 24 centimeters (Box 29, Folder 1)
    Creator: Hellige, Hendrik
  - Aladdin and the wonderful lamp and other stories Chicago, IL: W.B. Conkey., undated; 51 pages, 17 centimeters (Box 29, Folder 2)
    Children's book containing title story in addition to "The Story of the Fisherman and the Genie" and "The History of the Young King and the Black Isles."
  - Aladdin and the wonderful lamp and other stories New York, NY: A.L. Burt., undated; 51 pages, 22 centimeters (Box 29, Folder 3)
    Children's book containing title story in addition to other tales. Artwork and writing uncredited. Handwritten inscription dated 1919.
  - Aladdin wonder book Cincinnati, OH: Peter G. Thompson., 1881; unpaged, color illustrations, 26 centimeters (Box 29, Folder 4)
    Originally published in 1881, unclear if book is original or reprint. Book collects four tales: "Aladdin"; "Sinbad the Sailor"; "Blue Beard "; "Jack the Giant Killer." Source material and author unclear. Handwritten inscription dated March 11th, 1936.
  - Arabesque: narrative structure and the aesthetics of repetition in 1001 nights Evanston, IL: Northwestern University., 1991; 155 pages, 22 centimeters (Box 29, Folder 5)
    Creator: Naddaff, Sandra
    Scholarly book looking at the Arabian Nights from a literary perspective. Cover illustration by R. Smirke from 1811 Jonathan Scott translation.
  - Antonio's tales from the thousand and one nights New York, NY: Stuart, Tabori, and Chang., 1985; 143 pages, 30 centimeters (Box 30, Folder 1)
    Creator: Finamore, Roy
    Based on the Burton translation, book is a selection of tales with elaborate illustrations by Lopez.
  - Antonio's tales from the thousand and one nights New York, NY: Stuart, Tabori, and Chang., 1985; 143 pages, 30 centimeters (Box 30, Folder 1)
    Creator: Burton, Richard
  - Antonio's tales from the thousand and one nights New York, NY: Stuart, Tabori, and Chang., 1985; 143 pages, 30 centimeters (Box 30, Folder 1)
    Creator: Lopez, Antonio